# **JULIO CASTRO**

# Senior Software Engineer

+41 76 513 18 64 | julio.castro.dev@gmail.com | Zurich, Switzerland

# **SUMMARY**

Extensive experience in software engineering from startup to large corporate levels. Proven success leading teams in various technologies including Angular, React, Nodejs or Spring Boot, resulting in highly performing, harmonious and cohesive teams with deep technical and business knowledge. Succeeded in applying mathematical and scientific skills to drive and clarify intricate and complex business challenges, resulting in bigger, better and faster achievements.

# **SKILLS**

- <u>Languages:</u> Typescript, Java, Python, HTML/CSS, Javascript, SQL.
- <u>Technologies:</u> Angular, React, Spring Boot, Nodejs, Nextjs, Cypress.
- Other: Domain Driven Design, Clean Arquitecture, Modern Reactivity.

# **EXPERIENCE**

# Senior Software Engineer at Swisscom IAM | Zuhlke Group Jun 2022 - Present

- Led the frontend of a tribe of 25+ engineers, supporting, promoting and driving the adoption of best practices and cutting edge technologies.
- Introduced numerous improvements with direct impact on daily operations: reduced pipeline time by half, developed a tool that cut several hours of manual work to just 1 click, among others.
- Mentored up to 5 new colleagues and contributed to improve onboarding processes, reducing on average by two weeks the time in which a new member became a regular contributor.
- Played a crucial role in making both frontend and backend architectural decisions, achieved a huge reduction in complexity in reusing and nesting IAM flows, crucial business feature, allowing tasks that had weeks of estimation to be released to production within a day.
- <u>Skills:</u> TypeScript, Angular, Java, Spring Boot, Domain Driven Design, Bitbucket.

## Senior Software Engineer at We Feed Raw, a US pet food start up | Acid Tango Jun 2021 - Jun 2022

- Led, built and maintained the backend and most of the entire infrastructure, achieved a successful migration and launch, returning a +50% increase in users and also new project signings and extensions with the customer.
- Migrated the complex pet feeding algorithm to an efficient and easy to read and extend solution, it was even reused in another similar product for the UK.
- Contributed and collaborated closely with the frontend team, achieving record delivery performance in the company, even reaching to release features in production within minutes.

- Actively participated and led weekly company conferences sharing and teaching on a multitude of topics, achieving direct positive impact on 5+ different projects.
- Skills: TypeScript, React, Nextjs, Domain Driven Design, Nodejs, PostgreSQL, AWS, GitHub.

#### Frontend Developer at Openbank, Satander's digital bank | Fabrik Oct 2020 - Jun 2021

- Led the upgrade of the microfrontend dedicated to bank transfers, removing thousands of lines of legacy code and reducing related story point estimates by 80%.
- Became the go-to person for technical questions from both business and development.
- Skills: TypeScript, React, Microfrontends, Redux, Bitbucket.

#### Backend Developer at Santander Payment Hub | Fabrik Jul 2020 - Oct 2020

- Integrated microservices in 300+ engineers project focused on Santander's international payment system, achieving goals despite 5+ constraints while maintaining high quality standards.
- Implemented deployment support tool, reducing human errors by 80%.
- Skills: Java, Spring Boot, Kafka, Bitbucket, Microsoft Azure.

#### Frontend Developer at Santander Innovation Lab | Fabrik Feb 2020 - Jul 2020

- Participated in development tasks for a hybrid mobile application for Santander UK, outstanding with 50% above average delivery performance.
- Implemented the most important algorithm for user experience: the credit card refresh logic. Initially estimated in one week and delivered a robust and easy to maintain solution within a day.
- Skills: TypeScript, Angular, Ionic, GitLab.

#### **Quality Assurance Developer at Santander Innovation Lab | Fabrik** Sep 2019 - Feb 2020

- Automated the end-to-end regression tests of 4 hybrid mobile applications focused on the banking sector, resulting in a reduction from 2 weeks of manual work to 10 minutes of automatic execution, a milestone achieved for the first time in the team and in the whole company.
- Obtained the opportunity to work in the development team due to excellent performance, business knowledge and problem-solving skills.
- Skills: Java, Selenium, Appium, GitLab.

#### **EDUCATION**

# **Bachelor's Degree | Polytechnic University of Madrid** 2017 - 2021

Mathematics and Computer Science.

- Achieved an average score of 9/10.
- Awarded annual academic excellence on behalf of Madrid city the 4 consecutive years.

#### **LANGUAGES**

- English: C1.
- German: A2 B1.
- · Spanish: Native.

